foreign
19 pandemic has shifted behaviors of
Filipinos towards retirement planning
with more people now thinking long term
but 80 percent or nearly 8 million of
retiring Filipinos are not financially
prepared let's now have an exchange with
Richard Bates president and chief
executive officer of Manulife
Philippines Richard great to have you
with us on the program how is this
pandemic affected people's attitudes
towards money and financial planning
all right really good to be here thank
you very much
um excellent question I think you know
as you highlighted one of bsp statistics
about 80 percent uh not being prepared
for retirement with only 20 being
involved in government systems uh that
ninja and provide for retirement what we
find is that this pandemic has
accelerated people's thinking about what
retirement means
um The Importance of Being with family
the importance of uh making sure that
they are planning as best as possible uh
for the future I think what we found is
a shift over the course of the last 12
plus months where you've had individuals
in the past who might be about living
now and now you have individuals saying
well hold on a second how about living
for tomorrow right and are we prepared
for tomorrow so recently Manulife did a
survey
um which was we call the Asia 2021 Asia
care survey and in that we identified
the needs of Filipinos have definitely
uh definitely changed they've definitely
accelerated and looked much more to
boards retirement much more towards
recognizing they don't have sufficient
retirement planning in place and has
raised their awareness of we've got to
get something in place and again you
know planning for tomorrow
it's really good to know
um Richard that uh a majority of
Filipinos now believe that retirement
planning has become you know more
important since covid-19 and that's well
above the Asia average of more than 70
but Richard many Filipinos also have you
know limited budget uh particularly uh
over the course of this pandemic many
have lost their jobs uh many of their
salaries have been reduced
um explain to us with this in mind how
can they say for their health needs and
retirement going forward
yeah really really important it's just
been a tough tough period for many many
people uh and to me this is where the
value of life insurance is absolutely
essential uh to a society and to an
economy
um so what I think is important is when
you look at the products available and
making sure that we have enough
flexibility in our product so for
example Manulife has a product called
Health Flex which is a critical illness
product flexible different packages and
sizes depending on an individual's needs
we also have retirement planning product
uh products called for example Freedom
uh which again it's about spending time
with a customer and understanding what
their needs are so that they actually
scope and shape a product that is going
to be suitable for their journey and
everyone starts at a different point in
their Journey uh with kids without kids
planning for kids and all of these
elements must be taken into account when
you are trying to find that uh right
policy for you but the main thing is to
make sure that you're by looking for a
policy that has the highest degree of
flexibility around it that means we can
cover more and more Filipinos
it's really good to know that the
packages of Manulife could that be even
be as low as uh what 1000 to 1 500 a
month the question now is how do they
apply for these plans what requirements
do they need
yeah I mean I think it's uh obviously
through our through our agents through
our live planners are able to share and
give good solid advice uh on this uh we
also have a bank partner with China bank
and through uh relationship with China
Bank we're able to service their
customers too and I think what's
important is that to spend time with the
right agents spend time with the right
advisor who's going to give you the time
and understanding not try and push
something on you but actually listen to
what your needs are and more
specifically shape it and if your
affordability is one and a half thousand
pesos a month and then that's great and
we'll shape something around that to
help that and then in the future as
affordability changes we can change the
product design and the product sheet to
help help along that Journey
and that is really good news for our
kababayans who are listening to us right
now for their retirement plans there's a
lot of flexibility in terms of the
various packages that you offer and amid
these challenging times in our lives uh
Richard and companies having to be
nimble and having to innovate how has
Manulife adjusted to this new normal of
business
yes well as you can tell firstly I'm at
home
um and so like everybody else we are uh
you know we are working to support the
customers as much as possible we're
quite privileged in our industry that we
can be just set up through
digitalization processes that our agents
can be at home our customers can be at
home and the company can be at home and
we can still manage and service our
customers in terms of applications in
terms of claims uh in terms of any uh
you know any inquiries they have and
we're quite fortunate that our industry
allows that but in order for that to
happen it's the digitalization journey
that we've been on which we started
prior to the pandemic and really what
the pandemic has done is accelerated a
number of our digital initiatives that
we've put in place whether it's
providing electronic contracts
electronic claims systems uh being able
to take applications without anybody
having to meet face to face we put these
controls in place to be able to help
people stay safe and really uh protect
themselves as we go through this journey
I do think you know in the future as we
get back to Summer level of normality of
what we saw before and we're able to
then meet again in a safe environment we
will have at least a foundation of
Bedrock to give even more flexibility to
a customer if they wish to meet face to
face and they're allowed to and it's
safe we can offer that if they want to
do it virtually over a video call we can
allow for that as well and this all
comes down to the importance of
adjusting ourselves for what the
customer needs are
thank you so much for this exchange
Richard Bates the president and CEO of
Manulife Philippines